Lois Gibbs Love Canal Papers MS063
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Health studies, circa 1978 -- 2010; MS063.003; 6.5 Linear Feet 5 record cartons and 1 document box.
  - Love Canal Expert Advisory Committee correspondence and presentations, 1998 -- 1999; MS063.003.027.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Love Canal Expert Advisory Committee participant lists, 1998, 2001 -- 2002, 2006; MS063.003.027.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Love Canal Expert Advisory Committee members curriculum vitae, 1997; MS063.003.027.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Environmental exposure data presentation, circa 2000; MS063.003.027.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - Birthweight presentation, 2004; MS063.003.027.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Love Canal Expert Advisory Committee correspondence and minutes, 1998 -- 2003; MS063.003.027.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - Mortality study presentations and report, 2000 -- 2003; MS063.003.027.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 18)
  - 93rd street school presentation, circa 2000; MS063.003.027.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 19)
  - Reproductive outcomes presentation, circa 2000; MS063.003.027.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 20)
  - Serum Love indicator study correspondence and presentations, 1999 -- 2004; MS063.003.027.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 21)
  - Love Canal community meeting correspondence, meeting agenda, and reports, 2008; MS063.003.027.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - Love Canal Expert Advisory Committee correspondence and meeting agenda, 2000; MS063.003.027.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 23)
  - Love Canal Expert Advisory Committee correspondence and presentations, 2000; MS063.003.027.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 24)
  - Love Canal Expert Advisory Committee correspondence, memos, and notes, 2001; MS063.003.027.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 25)
  - Love Canal Expert Advisory Committee correspondence, notes, and presentations, 2000 -- 2002; MS063.003.027.00026; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 26)
  - Love Canal Expert Advisory Committee correspondence, notes, and presentations, 2002 -- 2004; MS063.003.027.00027; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 27)
  - Love Canal Medical Fund correspondence, meeting minutes, and notes, 1997 -- 2002; MS063.003.027.00028; 1 Folder(s) (Box 27, Folder 28)
  - Control population health questionnaire, circa 1978; MS063.003.029.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Relocation lists, circa 1978; MS063.003.029.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Daily listings mobile lab data, circa 1978; MS063.003.029.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Relocation review notes, 1979; MS063.003.029.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Health survey original, circa 1978; MS063.003.029.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - North End data, circa 1978; MS063.003.029.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Temporary relocation data and notes, circa 1978; MS063.003.029.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Environmental pregnancy data from Havana, Cuba correspondence, 1980; MS063.003.029.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Beverly Paigen research materials, 1978 -- 1979; MS063.003.029.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Health study data, circa 1978; MS063.003.029.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Love Canal clips, correspondence, and reports, 1990 -- 1992; MS063.003.029.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Superfund project, section 311 action correspondence and reports, 1979 -- 1980; MS063.003.029.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 18)
  - Environmental monitoring program correspondence and draft protocol, 1980; MS063.003.029.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 17)
  - Sorted listings by parameter, 1978 -- 1980; MS063.003.033.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 33, Folder 1)
- Publications and reports, circa 1978 -- 2010; MS064.004.000002; 5.4 Linear Feet 4.5 record cartons.
  This series consists of academic articles, books, booklets, case studies, correspondence, fact packs, guides, handbooks, programs, and technical memoranda. These materials largely document the Environmental Monitoring Program, Love Canal Habitability Study, and reports on the environmental conditions in the Love Canal. Other materials include publications on community organizing, environmental activism, and social justice. One particular useful grouping of materials is the Women's Activist kit in box 31.
  This series is arranged in two sub-series: Women's activist resources and Other publications. Within the sub-series, materials are arranged in received order.
  - Women's activism resources, 1978 -- 2010; MS063.004.001; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton.
    This sub-series is arranged in received order.
    Sub-series mainly includes guides, handbooks, booklets on community organizing, environmental justice, and social justice.
    This subseries is open for research.
    - Stop Environmental Cancer: An Epidemic of the Petrochemical Age guide, 1980; MS063.004.031.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Cards with a Punch, booklet, 1980; MS063.004.031.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Church Funds for Social Justice directory, circa 1983; MS063.004.031.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - National Clean Air Coalition's Activist Handbook, circa 1983; MS063.004.031.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Discover Total Resources: A Guide for Nonprofits, circa 1985; MS063.004.031.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Resources for Your Non-profit Organization: A How to do it Handbook, 1990; MS063.004.031.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - The Kid's Guide to Social Action: How to Solve the Social Problems You Choose - and turn Creative Thinking into Positive Action, 1991; MS063.004.031.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - A Troublemaker's Handbook, 1991; MS063.004.031.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Jobs and the Environment, draft, 1992; MS063.004.031.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Organizing for a Healthy Community: Conference Summary and Resource Guide, 1992; MS063.004.031.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Earth Budget: Making Our Tax Dollars Work for the Environment, 1993; MS063.004.031.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Guidebook for Community-based Strategic Planning for Empowerment Zones and Enterprise Communities, 1993; MS063.004.031.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - New Solutions: A Journal of Environmental and Occupational Health, 1993; MS063.004.031.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Organizing for Change, Changing to Organize, 1993; MS063.004.031.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Fighting Toxics in Your Community guide, 1993; MS063.004.031.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - Taking Action Against Toxics booklet, 1993; MS063.004.031.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 16)
    - Making the Environment Better Sierra Communications Manual, 1997; MS063.004.031.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - Nobody Particular: One Woman's Fight to Save the Bays, 2000; MS063.004.031.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - A Dialogue of Consequence: Citizen Groups and Higher Education, 2003; MS063.004.031.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - The Midnite School: Creating a Vision for Our Movement, 2004; MS063.004.031.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - Multinational Monitor Magazine 25th Anniversary Issue, 2005; MS063.004.031.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - Good Neighbor handbook, 2006; MS063.004.031.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 22)
    - Community Organizing booklet, circa 1978 -- 2010; MS063.004.031.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 31, Folder 23)
  - Other publications, 1979 -- 2004; MS063.004.002; 4.2 Linear Feet 3.5 record cartons.
    Sub-series mainly includes materials on the Environmental Monitoring Program, the Love Canal Habitability Study, and other reports on the environmental condition in Love Canal.
    This sub-series is open for research.
    - To Governor Hugh L. Carey and Members of the New York State Legislature, 1981; MS063.004.023.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Love Canal fact pack, 1997, 2004; MS063.004.023.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Love Canal A Special Report to the Governor and Legislature, 1981; MS063.004.023.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Exposure Assessment Using Environmental Data from Love Canal, 1981; MS063.004.023.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - Allan Mazur's A Hazardous Inquiry, 1995 -- 1997; MS063.004.023.00016; 3 Folder(s) (Box 23, Folder 16-18)
    - Love Canal Twentieth anniversary, 1998; MS063.004.023.00018; 4 Folder(s) (Box 23, Folder 21-24)
    - Love Canal: A Chronology of Events that Shaped a Movement, booklet, circa 1997; MS063.004.023.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - Twentieth Anniversary of Love Canal awards reception program, circa 1998; MS063.004.026.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Twenty fifth Anniversary of Love Canal awards ceremony program, 2003; MS063.004.026.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Love Canal: Don't Allow History to Repeat Itself, booklet, 1989; MS063.004.026.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - The Final White Wash at Love Canal, article, 2008; MS063.004.026.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Love Canal: A Bibliography, 1979; MS063.004.026.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Love Canal: A Chronology of Events that Shaped a Movement, 1984; MS063.004.026.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - Love Canal Remedial Project: Long-term monitoring program design task VB, final report, 1985; MS063.004.026.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - Final Report: Determination of Chemical Residues in Whole Blood of Selected Love Canal Area Residents, 1980; MS063.004.026.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Earthcare: lessons from Love Canal, guide, 1987; MS063.004.026.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - A Challenge for the 1980s preliminary, draft report, MS063.004.026.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - Site investigations and Remedial Action Alternatives, Love Canal raw data, 1983; MS063.004.026.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - Pilot Study for Love EDA Canal Habitability Study volume I, 1983; MS063.004.028.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Pilot Study for Love EDA Canal Habitability Study volume II, 1987; MS063.004.028.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Love Canal emergency Declaration Area Habitability study volume I, final report, 1988; MS063.004.028.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Love Canal emergency Declaration Area Habitability study volume II, final report, 1988; MS063.004.028.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Love Canal emergency Declaration Area Habitability study volume III, final report, 1988; MS063.004.028.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Love Canal emergency Declaration Area Habitability study volume IV, final report, 1988; MS063.004.028.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Love Canal emergency Declaration Area Habitability study volume V, final report, 1988; MS063.004.028.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Environmental Monitoring at Love Canal volume I, short report, 1982; MS063.004.028.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Environmental Monitoring at Love Canal volume I, report, 1982; MS063.004.028.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Environmental Monitoring at Love Canal volume II part one, report, 1982; MS063.004.028.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Environmental Monitoring at Love Canal volume II part two, report, 1982; MS063.004.028.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Environmental Monitoring at Love Canal volume III, report, 1982; MS063.004.028.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Love Canal Emergency Declaration Area Proposed Habitability criteria, 1986; MS063.004.028.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Emergency Management Toxic Waste Incident Response: Love Canal in Light of Superfund, 1982; MS063.004.028.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Report on Task 5: Exposure Assessment Using Environmental Data from Love Canal, draft, 1981; MS063.004.028.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Love Canal: The Truth Seeps Out, 1981; MS063.004.028.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - The Remedial Construction Project at Love Canal, Niagara Falls, New York: Findings and Comments, 1980; MS063.004.028.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - 609…and Counting, Hazardous Wastes and the Public's Health in New York State, report, 1980; MS063.004.029.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Ecumenical Task Force of the Niagara Frontier, Inc. progress report, 1980; MS063.004.029.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Interagency Task Force on Hazardous Wastes hearing officer's report, 1979; MS063.004.029.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Interagency Task Force on Hazardous Wastes, draft report, 1979; MS063.004.029.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Environmental Monitoring Program, report, 1980; MS063.004.029.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Environmental Monitoring at Love Canal Interagency review, 1982; MS063.004.029.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - Habitability of the Love Canal Area technical memorandum, 1983; MS063.004.029.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - An Inventory of Industrial Hazardous Waste Generation in New York State technical report, 1979; MS063.004.030.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Toxic Substances in New York's Environment technical report, 1979; MS063.004.030.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Environmental Monitoring Program, draft report, circa 1980; MS063.004.030.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Environmental Monitoring Program consultants review draft report, 1980; MS063.004.030.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Environmental Monitoring Program data report, 1980; MS063.004.030.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - The Ravaged River: Toxic Chemicals in the Niagara River report, 1981; MS063.004.030.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Overview of Environmental Pollution in the Niagara Frontier, New York, 1982; MS063.004.030.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Love Canal Remedial Project Long-Term Monitoring Program Design Volume I: Text, 1985; MS063.004.030.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Love Canal Remedial Project Long-Term Monitoring Program Design Volume II: Appendices, 1985; MS063.004.030.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Inactive Hazardous Waste Disposal Sites in New York State annual report, 1987; MS063.004.030.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Draft Generic Environmental Impact Statement for the Love Canal Area Master Plan, 1989; MS063.004.030.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Love Canal, 1989: Still Seeking a Solution case study, MS063.004.030.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Illegal Dumping in New York State: Who's Enforcing the Law report, 1991; MS063.004.030.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Love Canal Emergency Declaration Area: Remediation of EDA 2 and 3 Final Study report, 1991; MS063.004.030.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - Learning from Love Canal: A 20th Century Anniversary Retrospective, 1998; MS063.004.030.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - The Road to Love Canal: Managing Industrial Waste before EPA, 1996; MS063.004.030.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - Rashomon at Love Canal, draft, 1996; MS063.004.030.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 30, Folder 17)
- Awards, audiovisual materials, and ephemera, circa 1978 -- 2010; MS063.005; .2 Linear Feet 1 box.
  This series consists of a Gibbs and Collette certificate award, a pen and ink caricature of Lois Gibbs fighting toxic waste, and phonograph records sent to Lois Gibbs by Will Shatter and Steve Carron, musicians who wrote songs about Love Canal.
  - Will Shatter correspondence and 45 RPM record, 1982; MS063.005.016.00047; 1 Folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 47)
  - Steve Carron 45 RPM records and correspondence, 1983; MS063.005.016.00048; 1 Folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 48)
  - Gibbs and Collete certificate award, 1989; MS063.005.032.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Pen and ink caricature of Lois Gibbs fighting toxic waste, circa 1978 -- 2010; MS063.005.032.00002.000001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Pen and ink caricature of Lois Gibbs fighting toxic waste, undated; MS063.005.032.00002.000002; 1 Digital Object(s); 81.46 Megabytes
      Pen and ink caricature of Lois Gibbs fighting toxic waste